Hello.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome to Conf42 Observability 2026.
And this is my talk.
I'm going to be talking on the
topic that says, "The Fifth Golden
Signal: Making Accessibility
Observable." If you're wondering what
all of that means, just sit back.
In a few minutes, I'm going to be
explaining what I mean by all of this.
But before that, a quick disclaimer,
I don't feel too well, so I'm going
to try to be as audible as I can and
make the session as interactive and
engaging as possible so that it's not
just, It's fun for the both of us.
Excuse me.
So yeah, let's start off
with a bit of introduction.
So who is Victoria?
Sorry, give me a minute.
Yeah.
Again, hi.
My name is Victoria Nduka.
I currently work as a technical
support intern at Victoria Metrics.
Yes, I'm-- I-- my name is Victoria, and I
work at a company that has Victoria in it.
Yeah, it's funny.
It's a nice conversation starter.
But anyway, I have a
background in UX design.
I love to write and speak about things
that I love and that interest me.
Example, this talk.
I have a morbid fear of snakes.
I don't like snakes.
I think the word is, the
correct word is hate.
I hate reptiles generally,
but especially snakes.
I'm a big fan of Mikaela.
Really looking forward to season
five of "The Lincoln Lawyer" series.
Let me know if you're also
a fan in the comments.
I like to meet my people.
And if you'd like to learn more
about my work and who I am, check
out my website, victorianduka.com.
Now let's get into the
business of the day.
So before we talk about what the fifth
golden signal is, it only makes sense
that we cover or refresh our minds
about the four golden s- gold signals.
So we may already be familiar with
this, but for those of us who aren't,
what are the four golden signals?
So Google came up with this, and they
said if you must measure four signals
about your user-facing systems, these
are the four you should focus on.
And they are latency, which tells you
how long it takes to serve a request.
There's error that tells you
the rate of requests that fail.
Traffic lets you know how much demand
is being placed on your system.
Saturation tells you how full your system
is, how much of your resources are being
used up, and how quickly they can run out.
Excuse me.
So what do these signals tell you
about the health of your system?
Like, why do we need
to monitor the signals?
There are a couple of reasons
why we monitor them, and one of
them is that they measure what
the user actually experiences.
So it's user it's user-focused.
Let's take latency, for instance.
You are measuring latency.
Latency tells you how long it takes for a
user request that's in engineering terms.
But on user end, it's, Translates
or it appears as a lag.
So it's a slow responding page.
I go to your landing page and it
takes a long time for it to load.
That's frustrating for the user.
And so that's one of the reasons why we
measure latency, to help you know what
the user is experiencing on their own end.
So the second reason is it helps
you detect problems early on.
Performance drops and failures before
users start complaining about them.
It helps you
troubleshoot faster, they lower
the time that it takes to detect
and fix system issues, and also
helps you with capacity planning.
You'll be able to predict when
your system will run out of
resources under heavy load.
So saturation, if you're measuring
saturation, you know what your CP
capacity is and when the traffic is
too much and you need to scale to
accommodate the higher traffic coming in.
So all in all it makes you proactive, it
shows that you care less about the user.
So if you really think about it, that
the four signals that we talked about,
latency, error, traffic, saturation,
all have UX at the core of it.
At the center of it is our empathy
for the users ultimately UX motivation
is behind both a lot of the things
that have been running so…
But we have found that there's a group
of users who have been re-historically
marginalized or unintentionally
excluded, and whose experiences are
rarely in focus when we're designing
s-software or systems, and these
are persons with disabilities.
So it's not that these four signals
that we're measuring, that we're
measuring don't affect these users.
They actually do.
If you-- If there's a, if the latency
is high, that means that your website
will be slow, and that is frustrating
for everyone, not just a per- not
just persons with disabilities.
So these affect them as well.
But the point is that these signals
don't tell us whether a person
with disability can actually use
your software when it's available.
Like all things being equal, if there
are no issues with latency is still
okay, it's not rising, there are no
errors traffic is… you have enough
resources to manage traffic, it still
doesn't tell you whether a person using a
screen reader can navigate your website.
It doesn't tell you whether a
person with a motor impairment
can use your tool or your product.
And so because of that, first you
may not really know what I- what the
experience like, is like for those people.
You can't since you're not
tracking it as one of the signals.
So yeah.
And what is it called when you put
into consideration people who have
disabilities when you build products?
I think the word for it is accessibility.
So this is a very common
term, but something.
But for it for a word that's so
common, it's often very much evolved.
We are very conversant
with this symbol here.
It shows a person on a wheelchair
that is like symbol for
accessibility in most cases.
But for the purpose of this
talk, I'm going to be focusing
on digital accessibility.
So digital accessibility means that your
content or your product can be perceived,
understood, and navigated by everyone,
including persons with disabilities.
And these include people who are blind,
who have low vision, who are deaf or hard
of hearing, who have motor impairments,
or who have cognitive differences Now
we've expla- we, we explained what
accessibility is, it only makes sense
that we find out what's the other
big word is, that is observability.
And I'm sure some of us already know
what as- observability is, but for
the sake of those who don't but it's
for the sake of the, the newbies like
me, observability is the ability to
understand a system's internal states
or condition by analyzing what it
produces, its external out- outputs.
And
those outputs are in the form
of logs, metrics, and traces.
So something to think about.
If accessibility is about the user
experience, and we've seen that the
signals, the foreground signals that
we monitor have user experience at
the core of it, and we already have
a system to continuously understand
system health, could we not just do
the same thing for accessibility?
Let's find out how might we measure
how well people with disability
can use a product and service?
So in other words, how-- what observable
outputs indicates accessibility or
indicates that a product is accessible?
For it to observe you need to have data.
So we want to find out how
accessibility is typically measured.
Now accessibility I'm sorry I need
to redu- reduce how fast I talk.
Accessibility is subjective, so it's not
something that you can directly measure.
But there are frameworks or guidelines
or standards against which we can
measure how accessible a product
or a digital service or product is
And one of those frameworks
is the WCAG standard.
WCAG is W-C-A-G, and it stands for Web
Content Access- Accessibility Guideline.
So that was put together by the
World Wide Web Consortium . And
so a lot of the measurements,
accessibility measurements Come from
are based off of these principles.
So the WCAG is basically a set
of principles, and then also
further broken down into success
criteria, success cri- criteria.
So it's basically like a
checklist that you need to use to
confirm, does my website do this?
Does my website do that?
Does it do this, does it do that?
To help you determine how easy it is
for people who have disabilities to
navigate your product or your website.
So with that in mind, we have a couple
of ways, like a couple of things that
people measure to know if something
or a product is really accessible.
One of it is compliance percentage.
So we are checking, make sure, like it's
basically indicates how much of a system
successfully passes a set of rule lists.
So for example, you can say that a
website sat- satisfies 85% of the 50
required WCAG level AA checkpoints.
And then there is health and
quality scores, which is… I
think that's the more common one.
When you run Google Lighthouse scan,
it gives you this scoring over 100
from from zero to 100, and usually
by automated tools like Lighthouse,
ObservePoint or Siteimprove.
So that's another way you
can measure accessibility.
And then there's error density
that measures the frequency of
accessibility issues, frequency of
accessibility issues relative to
the size or scope of the website.
So instead of looking at the raw number
of errors, for example, instead of
let's say if you have 1,000 errors if
you have 1,000 errors on a two-page
site and you have 1,000 errors on a
1,000, 1,000-page site, just an example,
the density for a two-page site is
definitely going to be higher error
density helps you to normalize data.
It is usually calculated as the
number of the average number of
errors found per page, so that way
it's we- evenly dis- distributed.
And the next one is conformance
levels, and this is also part
of the WCAG, WC- WCAG standards.
So they have different levels.
There's level A, which
is the bare minimum.
Level AA, which is the standard
that everybody must meet.
And then there's AAA, sorry.
Then there's level AAA, which
tells, which is like what we,
what everyone should strive for
So it acts as a milestone for how
thoroughly a website removes barriers.
So these are-- We can already
see that we can get data.
Like there are some things, there
are some things that indicate how
accessible a website or a product…
why do I keep saying website?
A product is.
So what would accessibility
metric or telemetry look like?
First, you need to generate it
like we do with all of our all
of the things that we monitor.
So how do we generate this?
From the previous slide, we already
see what some of the data that you
can get from accessibility tests.
And yeah, you could run accessibility
checks with automated tools.
You could do manual checks and then
get the results of those over time.
So you have gotten the data that you need.
You also need to then collect it somehow.
And for this you already have
tools, thankfully to help us
through this pipeline to collect
access-accessibility telemetry.
And for collection, we could
use VM agents or Prometheus to
scrape or push to a storage base.
Yeah Or one telemetry tool.
These are open source tools, so
it's free and you can use them
without paying any without paying
anything, at no cost to you.
Then you also need a way to store
this data that you've collected.
So this brings in the time series
database like Metriums, Prometheus, and
some other proprietary tools that exist.
And you also need a way to visualize it.
Now, this is where you have your
dashboards and stuff, and for
this you can use Grafana or any
other tool that works for you.
This is not something that…
This is not just something
that I did out of curiosity.
I also had to test it out myself,
experiment with it and see if it
actually works, and share with you
what it could look like in practice.
So for my own implementation, I use GitHub
Actions to run axe-core on our website,
my personal website that I shared at
the beginning of the talk every day.
So axe-core runs on the website every day
to check for accessibility and then saves
the results on Graphite, then sends it to
Grafana Cloud where I can visualize it.
So I now present dashboards
for, to monitor certain metrics or
indicators that are important for me.
So you can… This is the link to the
repo and to the workflow, the GitHub
workflow, GitHub Actions workflow that
I used for this little experiment.
And I just want to say this is just
one possible way of doing this.
It mustn't follow, it mustn't
use the exact tools I used.
You could… There are a lot of
ways that you could implement this.
You could use different tools for
different stages of the process.
So yeah a little demonstration of
what's the experimentation look like.
This is my website.
It's a simple webpage with
mostly with text and links.
So it's a three-page website.
There's a
homepage, then there's the
About Us and the Works page.
So at a glance, you can alr-
you can already tell that there
are some issues with this.
The font, the date is font
against the white background.
The font gray color against
the white background.
So when I first ran the test, it's
created a-- I saw that there were a couple
of issues with it, and this dashboard
shows what some of those issues are.
You can see that what I'm tracking now
are the total number of violations by
page, accessibility violations over time.
This is the one that shows you the
trends, whether you are regressing
or not, and violations by severity.
And this is just for my
own personal projects.
So for your organization, like
it could be completely different.
Like you you know the metrics that
you want to track, you know that
are relevant to your organization.
So do what suits you.
So at a glance, you can tell that I have a
lot of accessibility issues on my website
and a lot of violations on my website.
And the bulk of them are
serious issues, and majority
of them are on the works page.
So after I made changes, after I improved
the website so that it is, it- so that
it meets a lot more of the accessibility
guidelines set out by WCAG, this is
what the dashboard now looks like.
So the accessibility issues, the, the
violations reduced from forty-three
to thirteen, and you can see here
that there's a drop, 71.4% drop.
And then the violations by page,
the works page has re- has reduced
to just two violations per page.
And then if you look at the graph, you can
see that it has dropped to this blue line.
This blue, yeah, line that represents
works has dropped from about twenty-three
to less than five And this is something
that if you weren't tracking, you
can't, you probably, you didn't
have known that this is the effect.
And when it, when a, when an issue
is introduced, when an accessibility
issue is introduced, you can't also
tell because you're not monitoring it.
So like this is a, this is me trying
to make a case for why it's necessary
for you to observe accessibility.
And I've tested it and I've tried it out.
There-- We have the tools
that we need to make it work.
We just need to have that mindset.
We just need to care enough for
these users with disab- these
users with disability to add.
It's just, it could be j-just one
extra panel to your dashboard.
It could be one of it could be
just two, but it's not too much to
ask if you really care about users
equally as you're claiming to do.
So yeah this is the link to the dashboard.
You can scan the code if you want
to or go to this website to view
the dashboard on your own device.
So we have talked about the
four golden signals latency,
traffic, error, and saturation.
So what would now be
the fifth golden signal?
Is it accessibility?
So I said accessibility is subjective
and you can't actually measure it
directly, but from what we've seen,
like there are other, there are
indicators, there are metrics that you
can measure that gives an indication
of how accessible your website is.
So the, this-- I'm not going to hand
you a formula for what the fifth
signal is or should be, because
I don't think there's one number
that works for every organization.
So what, but what I would say is
this, it's what, like whatever you
decide to use to track accessibility,
it should have the same shape as
the other four golden signals.
It should be a measurable rate that is
tracked over time, and that tells you
when something's gotten worse before
a user can, a, a user has to tell you.
So maybe for you that's a severity
weighted validation rate like mine.
It could also be something more
specific to your product, maybe time to
remediate or percentage of critical user
flows that pass screen reader tests.
It's for you to decide, or this is
something for you to think about.
So as you leave this talk, what
do I want you to take home?
Or what would you like to
do next or keep in mind?
Try to audit your current processes.
Are you getting static reports or
are you already collecting continuous
data from your accessibility test?
Try out what I've just done, but on
a small project first if you are not
sure if you want to commit to it.
So you could run the controls
with this experiment like I did.
I'm not suggesting that every team
needs to build exactly what I built,
but the point is that start somewhere.
If you-- if you already have the data,
get what's the… Don't-- it doesn't
take more, it doesn't take much to just
test it out and see how much it improves
the user experience for your users,
particularly those with disabilities.
And then share what you've just learned
at this talk with your colleagues
or your managers or your teammates.
If after testing and that it works,
it looks like something promising
that you'd want to do long term,
then you can expand from there.
So yeah.
Couple of resources.
There's a Google S-SRE book
that talks about the four golden
signals if you'd like to read it.
And then there's WCAG 2.1
guidelines if you want to
learn more about accessibility.
And that's all.
Thank you for coming to my TED Talk.